<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
    "/usr/share/sgml/docbook/dtd/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>

<article lang="en">
    <articleinfo>
        <title>Asterisk Desktop Manager</title>
        <subtitle>User Guide</subtitle>
        <author>
            <firstname>Adrien</firstname>
            <surname>Barilly</surname>
            <email>adrien.barilly@adm.hamnett.org</email>
        </author>
        <abstract>
            <para>
                This document will guide the new user along the necessary steps
                of configuring and running Asterisk Desktop Manager.
            </para>
        </abstract>
    </articleinfo>

    <section id="intro">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            Welcome to Asterisk Desktop Manager, the simple, effective, open source application
            to manage your VoIP telephony!
        </para>
        <para>
            Asterisk Desktop Manager, or <emphasis>ADM</emphasis> for short, is the simplest way 
            to integrate Voice Over IP to your desktop: quietly sitting in the system tray, ADM
            watches your phones and allows you to effectively control them in a few clicks. But ADM
            can do more: you can store your contacts in its integrated phonebook,
            automatically turn down the music on new calls, connect your Bluetooth phone,
            or even pop up the browser with more information on who's calling.
        </para>
        <para>
            In this document, we will go through the basic steps of configuring ADM and connecting
            it to your phones. This is not at all complicated, but, before we go into it, there are
            a few things you need to know about Asterisk Desktop Manager.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="howadmworks">
        <title>How ADM works</title>
        <para>
            If you are reading this, you probably already know that your VoIP phones are connected
            to a PBX, and this PBX is certainly called Asterisk.
        </para>
        <para>
            Asterisk provides an interface for external programs to manage the connected phones;
            this interface is called the Manager Interface, and it must be enabled in the configuration
            of Asterisk. Ask the administrator of your PBX to know if this interface is enabled; if you
            are this administrator, please refer to Asterisk's documentation on how to do this.
        </para>
        <para>
            When launched, ADM will connect to this interface, and then be able to listen for events,
            like new phone calls, and send commands to the PBX. If you tell ADM how your phone is
            identified to the PBX, ADM can tell you for example that someone is calling you,
            or can order the PBX to make a call from your phone to any other number. All of these
            features, and much more, are packed in one simple application that we are going to
            configure now.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="configuring">
        <title>Configuring ADM</title>
        <para>
            Let us first assume that you have downloaded and installed Asterisk Desktop Manager
            on your workstation. If not, you can find the Linux or Windows packages on
            <ulink url="http://adm.hamnett.org">http://adm.hamnett.org</ulink> in the
            <guimenu>Downloads</guimenu> section; pick up the one for your architecture,
            and install it.
        </para>
        <para>
            When you launch Asterisk Desktop Manager for the first time, a new configuration
            file will be created, and ADM will ask you to enter some information on your
            PBX and your phones. Later, to go back to the configuration panel, simply right-click
            on ADM's tray icon, and in the <guimenu>Configurations</guimenu> submenu, click
            <guimenuitem>Edit current</guimenuitem>.
        </para>
        <para>
            In this configuration panel you will see several menus on the left; you already guessed
            that the most important one is <guimenu>Asterisk</guimenu>. Open this menu and choose
            <guisubmenu>Manager</guisubmenu>: this is where we tell ADM how to connect to the manager
            interface of Asterisk. You will be asked to enter the address, or host name, of the PBX
            (forget about the port; it is almost always <parameter class="option">5038</parameter>,
            the default value). Then, you need to
            know how to identify to this PBX; ask your PBX administrator for what to put as user name
            and password.
        </para>
        <para>
            Once ADM knows how to connect to the PBX, the next step is to tell it which phone
            your are using to make calls. This is done in the <guisubmenu>Extensions</guisubmenu> panel.
            There, you will have to enter some information about this phone:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        the source channel of your phone; usually, this is something like
                        <parameter class="option">SIP/1000</parameter> or <parameter class="option">IAX2/1234</parameter>;
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        the context that is assigned to this phone;
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        and the priority, which is certainly <parameter class="option">1</parameter>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            Again, your PBX administrator knows all of this, and can tell you exactly what to put
            in these fields.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you have more than one phone, ADM can also watch them: add their channels to the
            parameter called <guimenuitem>My Channels</guimenuitem>, and separate each value by a
            comma ('<parameter>,</parameter>'). <!--This can be very useful in an office, where you would like to turn down
            the music automatically when one of your collegues is getting a call.-->
            Don't forget to put your main phone here too.
        </para>
        <para>
            There are many other features that you can configure in ADM. Have a look at the other
            pages in the configuration panel and play with them a bit. These should be self-explanatory,
            but you can take a look at <xref linkend="features"/> later for more information.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="using">
        <title>Using ADM</title>
        <para>
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="features">
        <title>Advanced features</title>
        <para>
        </para>
    </section>
</article>
